<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Margins at the Centre</title>
            <title type="sub">Book Production and Practices of Annotation in the East Frankish Realm
               (ca. 830-900)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Cinzia Grifoni</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>At the beginning of the ninth century CE the Carolingian Empire encompassed large parts
            of what is now Western Europe. As early as the 830s, however, a process of political
            fragmentation began which led to the creation of the West, the Middle and the East
            Frankish Kingdom. These developed into independent units, despite formally remaining
            part of the Empire until 888.</p>
         <p>The project "<hi rend="strong">Margins at the Centre</hi>" focuses on the East Frankish Kingdom and examines whether the process leading to political independence also entailed a new self-consciousness in the cultural sphere, i.e. whether East Frankish scholars developed their own approaches, especially with regard to the study of Latin and the Bible. These were the two disciplines which were most thoroughly addressed in the Middle Ages. The Bible, which circulated in Latin in Western Europe, was the point of reference for moral, social, political and spiritual life. Therefore, it formed the main subject of scholarly interest in this period. Command of Latin was essential to understand the Bible's text, its message, and the numerous explanations written by Christian exegetes over the centuries. While Latin in its medieval forms was still spoken in many regions of the Carolingian Empire, it was a foreign language in the East Frankish Kingdom. Here it had to be learnt from scratch by studying grammar.</p>
         <p>With all this being considered, <hi rend="strong">the main questions addressed </hi>by the project are: Did East Frankish scholars teach Latin differently from their contemporary fellows because of the different linguistic setting of their audiences? Did they find a particular way to communicate the contents of the Bible to their students and to those members of the lay elite who could read and understand Latin? Did they take into account possible difficulties of their East Frankish public when writing down their explanations of Latin grammar and the Bible? The existence of a peculiar East Frankish approach to Latin and the Bible has so far been asserted by relying on the study of the contemporary glosses and literary output in Old High German. The far more numerous and extensive interpretations in Latin, however, have rarely been investigated in order to verify and substantiate such a statement.</p>
         <p/>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>The investigation will begin in the monasteries of St. Gall and Wissembourg during the time of Grimald's abbacy (ca. 833-872). It will initially concentrate on annotated manuscripts of both the Bible and of Priscian's <hi>Institutiones Grammaticae</hi>, some of them in fragmentary form. In a further step, contemporary books of the same format, which were produced both within and outside the East Frankish Kingdom, will be compared.</p>
         <p><hi rend="strong">The provisional list of manuscripts which will be taken into account comprises:</hi></p>
         <list>
            <item>Augsburg, Archiv des Bistums, HS 6</item>
            <item>Camaldoli, Arch., s.n. + Oslo, Schøyen Coll., 620</item>
            <item>Dillingen, Studienbibliothek Fragm. 25 + Oslo, Schøyen Collection, 74</item>
            <item>Firenze, Biblioteca Medicea Laurenziana, Ashb. 54</item>
            <item>Frankfurt, Stadt- und Universitätsbibliothek, Barth. 32</item>
            <item>Göttweig, Stiftsbibliothek, Cod. 30</item>
            <item>Ivrea, Biblioteca Capitolare, LXXIX (28)</item>
            <item>Laon, Bibliothèque Municipale, Ms. 14</item>
            <item>München, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Clm 29315/3 + Regensburg, Bischöfliche
               Zentralbibliothek, Fragm. IV.2.1 + Praha, Národní galerie, Inv. Nr. K 7314</item>
            <item>Orléans, Bibliothèque Municipale, Ms. 48</item>
            <item>St. Gallen, Stiftsbibliothek, Cod. 27</item>
            <item>St. Gallen, Stiftsbibliothek, Cod. 41</item>
            <item>St. Gallen, Stiftsbibliothek, Cod. 50</item>
            <item>St. Gallen, Stiftsbibliothek, Cod. 1395, p. 440-441</item>
            <item>Troyes, Bibliothèque Municipale, Ms. 615</item>
            <item>Vercelli, Biblioteca Capitolare, LXII (2)</item>
            <item>Vercelli, Biblioteca Capitolare, CXLIX (136)</item>
            <item>Wien, Österreichische Nationalbibliothek, Cod. 1239</item>
            <item>Wolfenbüttel, Herzog August Bibliothek, 26 Weiss.</item>
            <item>Wolfenbüttel, Herzog August Bibliothek, 32 Weiss.</item>
            <item>Wolfenbüttel, Herzog August Bibliothek, 33 Weiss.</item>
            <item>Wolfenbüttel, Herzog August Bibliothek, 36 Weiss.</item>
            <item>Wolfenbüttel, Herzog August Bibliothek, 47 Weiss.</item>
            <item>Wolfenbüttel, Herzog August Bibliothek, 50 Weiss. (Priscians <hi>Institutiones
                  Grammaticae</hi>)</item>
            <item>Wolfenbüttel, Herzog August Bibliothek, 59 Weiss.</item>
            <item>Zürich, Zentralbibliothek, Ms. C 49 (Priscians <hi>Institutiones
               Grammaticae</hi>)</item>
            <item>Zürich, Zentralbibliothek, Ms. C 129</item>
            <item>Zürich, Staatsarchiv, W3.19.XII</item>
         </list>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
